中文字幕：dottob
<b><i>Psagmeno.com</b> <font color=#ff0000>Subtitles / Screenshots / Trailers</font>
派拉蒙影业
Paramount
维亚康姆公司
A VIACOM COMPANY
工厂[葡语]电影[西语]
FÁBRICA DE CINE
通路实业电影
<font color=#ff0000>A</font>ccess <font color=#ff0000>I</font>ndustries FILM
译者注
1549年，天主教传教士
圣·弗朗西斯·泽维尔
(Saint Francis Xavier)
在日本鹿儿岛开始传教
1613年，德川家康发布禁教令，幕府在全国禁止天主教
长崎云仙山区成为屠杀长崎地区天主教徒的场所
岛原天主教徒劫难始于此时
引自：http://blog.sina.com.cn/s/blog_3f8e0f520101iauv.html
译者注
1627年，松仓重政首创了“云仙地狱”的拷问方式
将教徒倒悬温泉正上方，受高温硫磺毒气熏蒸
在其气绝之前拖上缓和呼吸后，再吊回原位继续折磨
引自：http://www.sanada.net.cn/shiliao/shiliao_38.htm
译者注
1629年，水野守信首先于长崎实践以“踏绘”形式识别天主教徒的做法
所谓“踏绘”，即把圣像置于受检人面前，强迫践踏
引自：http://www.sanada.net.cn/shiliao/shiliao_38.htm
译者注
“穴吊”：将囚犯捆绑倒吊，头部插入大小如缸深坑
耳后开口让血缓慢渗出，再用似枷木具从脖子两侧封住坑口
埋住头部，持续多日致死
译者注
1634年，日本爆发反横征暴敛，反宗教迫害的农民大起义，即
“岛原(、天草)之乱”
引自：http://www.qulishi.com/huati/daoyuanzl/
沉默
Silence
赞美您，我主耶稣基督
Praise to you, Lord Jesus Christ
开始
始め
1633，主的平安[拉丁语]，赞美神
1633. Pax Christi. Praised be God.
虽然于我们，如今此地再无和平
Although for us. There is little peace in this land now.
我从未了解日本，当它成为文明之都
I never knew Japan, when it was a country of light.
但我没想到它会如当前这般黑暗
But I have never known it to be as dark as it is now.
我们所有进展都被新的迫害终止...
All our progress has ended in new persecution...
新的镇压，新的苦难
New repression, new suffering.
他们使用有洞的杓子(长柄勺)
They use ladles filled with holes,
好让水慢慢漏出
So the drops would come out slowly,
使痛苦持续更久
And the pain would be prolonged.
每滴溅落的水花
Each small splash of the water,
有如滚碳
Was like a burning coal.
长崎奉行官抓了四名修士(奉行：大小藩的地方官)
The Governor of Nagasaki took four friars,
和我们在云仙的一个自属教会
and one of our own society to Unzen.
那里有温泉
There are hotsprings there.
日本人称之为：“云仙地狱”
The Japanese call them: Hells
一方面，我以为，讲笑
Partly, I think, in mockery.
又一方面，我必须告诉你，讲真
and partly, I must tell you, in truth.
官员们要我们的教士抛弃神及神的爱的福音
The officials told our Padres to abandon God and the gospel of his love.
然而他们不只是拒绝弃教
But they not only refused to apostatize.
他们要求受折磨
They asked to be tortured.
这样，他们就可以证明他们信仰的力量
So they could demonstrate the strength of their faith
而神将与他们同在
and the presence of God within them.
有些留在山上，长达33天
Some remained on the mountain, for 33 days.
他们的勇气故事把希望给了我们的传教士
The story of their courage gives hope to those of us priests
那些潜藏此处者
who remain here in secret.
我们不会抛弃我们潜藏的基督徒
We will not abandon our hidden Christians.
那些身陷恐惧者
Who live in fear.
我们只会变得更强，籍由主爱
We only grow stronger in his love.
费雷拉和我们失联
Ferreira is lost to us.
这是他最后一封信
This was his last letter.
为何失联？
Why lost?
此信送交我处，正值你旅行葡萄牙之际
This letter came to us, when you were traveling from Portugal.
它经年始至我处，被藏匿、走私、赎回
It took years to reach us, it was hidden, smuggled, ransomed.
最终交至我手则由一位荷兰商贩
And finally put into my hand by a Dutch trader,
那位同携其它消息者
Who had other news as well.
他活着吗
He is alive?
传闻他已弃教
That he apostatized.
据说他公开谴责神，抛弃了其信仰
That he denounced God in public and abandoned his faith.
如今已成为一名日本人
And is now living as a Japanese.
那不可能
That's not possible.
神父费雷拉冒死于日本各地传播我等信仰
Father Ferreira risked his life to spread our faith all over Japan.
我们有今天都因为他
We're here today because of him.
是的，他曾是...他是我们中最强大的
Yes, he was... he is the strongest of us.
他写下那些话，正值所有迫害最为彻底
He wrote those words during the most sweeping persecution of all.
现在情况则更糟
Now things are even worse.
数千人死去
Thousands are dead.
因为我们带给他们那些
Because of what we brought them.
还有数千人已放弃他们的信仰
Thousands more have given up their faith.
你是说这商贩带来消息，只是未经证实，是吗
You said this trader brought news, but it's not proven, is it?
它可能是个诽谤以深入瓦解我等信仰
It could be a slander created to further discredit our faith.
考虑到该国的迫害程度
Given the extent of the persecution in that country.
恕我失敬，那里定有大众仍需我们
Respectfully, there must multitudes there who need us too.
而事实上，信中他再无多言
And the fact, there has been no other word of him.
- 至于那些消息经由荷兰...- 谣言，神父，只是
- And the news brought by the Dutch... - Rumors, Father, only.
我必须推断，那是真的
I must conclude, it is true.
-如果是真的，神父
-If it is true, Father.
那它意味着啥
What would it mean?
对耶稣会，对于整个欧洲的天主教
For the Jesuits. For the whole of Catholic Europe?
在我看来，我们此番使命，紧迫尤胜以往
It's seems to me that our mission here, is more urgent than ever.
我们得去找到神父费雷拉
We must go find Father Ferreira.
我不允许那样
I can not allow that.
怎，我们怎能放弃我们的使命
How. How can we abandon our mission?
你们的使命，神父加佩
Your mission, Father Garupe,
是找到费雷拉的消息，你已找到了
was to find word of Ferreira, you have found it.
-原谅我神父，只是这封信
-Excuse me Father, but this letter
讲述了最可怕的故事
Relates the most terrible story,
却只字未提费雷拉本人
but it says nothing of Ferreira himself.
他出了啥事仍是未知
Whatever happened to him is still unknown.
我们所知其命运的全部，只是这诽谤
All that we know of his fate, is this one slander.
请允许我，神父范礼安，但
Permit me, Father Valignano, but
我相信我们的使命依然成立
I believe our mission still stands.
你可知有多少基督徒？在岛原半岛被当局处决
Do you know how many Christians, the authorities executed in Shimabara?
数千人，数以万计
Thousands, tens of thousands.
他们大多数被斩首
Most of them beheaded.
不，对你们来说太危险了
No, it's far too dangerous for you.
是，但神父
Yes, but Father,
我们怎能忽视那个以信仰养育我们的人
how can we neglect the man who nurtured us in faith?
他为我们塑造了世界
He shapes the world for us.
即使诽谤是真的
And even if the slander should be true
而神父费雷拉有罪。-是的
then Father Ferreira is damned. - Yes.
我们别无选择除了拯救他的灵魂
We have no choice but to save his soul.
- 这是你们俩真心所想？-是的
- This is in your hearts in both of you? - Yes.
是的
It is.
有如我们当初的热诚
Like our first fervor.
那我必须相信是神安排它在那儿
Then I must trust God has put it there.
他招唤你们来场伟大的考验
He calls you to a great trial.
一旦你们涉足该国
The moment you set foot in that country,
你们步入险境
you step into high danger.
你们将是派往的最后两位传教士
You will be the last two priests to go.
两个人的军队
An army of two.
3月25日，1640。主的平安，神的荣誉
May 25th, 1640. Pax Christi, God be praised.
神父范礼安，当我写下这些字句
Father Valignano, as I begin these lines.
我不肯定它一旦完成，它还能抵达你处
I can not be sure that once they are done, they will ever reach you.
但我想保持您对我们使命的信心
But I want to maintain your confidence in our mission.
及证明您对我们的信任
And vindicate your faith in us.
今天，有个极好的消息
Today, there was wonderful news.
您的常先生找到艘中国船
Your Mr.Chiong has found us a Chinese boat.
它将偷运我们去日本
It will smuggle us into Japan.
他还说他在澳门找到了唯一的日本人
And he claims he's found the only Japanese in Macau.
可当我们在该国的最佳向导
To be our most valued guide in that country.
来吧，这边
Come on，this way.
最后，我们见到了首位日本人
Finally, we meet our first Japanese.
他不贵，你会明白
He is not much, you will see.
但差不多两月了，他是唯一的一个
But after almost two months, he is the only one.
醒醒
Wake up!
来吧，起来
Come on, get up!
他在海上漂流，葡萄牙人救了他
He was drifting on sea. Portuguese bring him.
他被困此处，想要回家
He's stuck here. Wants to go home.
是他？你真是日本人
Is he? Are you really Japanese?
他们会带你回家
They will take you home.
你家在哪儿
Where is your home?
长崎
Nagasaki.
你干哪行
What's your work?
你叫他干啥都行
He will do what you say.
你懂我们的话
You know our language?
懂点
Little.
是的，懂点
Yes. Little.
你从耶稣会教士学的
You learned from the Jesuit Padres,
你一定曾，因此
you must have, so...
你是基督徒
You're Christian.
不
No!
不是基督徒
No Christian.
好向导归你，他也是基督徒
Good guide for you, he's Christian too.
我不是基督徒
I am not Christian!
基督徒死了
Christians die!
他们死在长崎了
They die in Nagasaki.
-听我说
-Listen to me.
我们有钱
We have money.
如你肯帮我们，我们就带你回家
If you can help us, we can take you home
我们就带你回日本的家
We can take you home to Japan,
你想回日本的家吗
would you like to go home to Japan?
我想
I want.
我想回家
I want to go home.
不要钱
No for money!
日本是我的祖国
Japan is the country of my family!
我求你，别抛弃我，神父
I beg you, don't abandon me here, Father.
拜托
Please!
带我回家
Take me home.
他会是个好向导
He will be good guide.
答应我。-我给你洗洗！他们带我回家
Promise me. -I'll clean you up! They take me home.
答应我
Promise me.
我们的向导
Our guide.
他不是基督徒
He can't be Christian.
他说他不是，但你能信他所说的一切？
He says he's not, but can you believe anything he says?
我甚至不愿相信他是日本人
I don't even want to believe he is Japanese.
他又对他们说：你们要到全世界去，
And he said to them: Go ye into the whole world，
(注：《兰斯杜埃版圣经》马可福音 第16章第15节[Douay-Rheims Bible 16:15])
...将福音传给众生。
...and preach the gospel to every (living) creature.
(注：该版本无括号内单词)
甚至有如此人
Even to one such as this.
所以我们的主吩咐过
So our Lord commanded.
而当我准备如他所托，我看到他的脸在我面前
And as I prepare to do his work, I see his face before me.
他看起来像当他必须吩咐彼得时
He looks as he must have when he commanded Peter.
喂养我的羊羔
"Feed My lambs."
(注：约翰福音 21:15)
喂养我的羊羔，喂养我的羊
"Feed my lambs.""Feed my sheep."
(注：约翰福音 21:15,17)
这震撼了我
It fascinates me.
我感受到对他伟大的爱
I feel such great love for him.
加佩和我当然没行李带往日本
Garrpe and I had absolutely no luggage to bring to Japan.
除了我们自己的心
Except our own hearts.
在航行的平静和风暴中
And during the calm and storm of the voyage.
我回想过去的20年
I reflected upon the 20 years which has passed
自从迫害爆发以来
since the persecution has broken out.
日本的黑土地充满了那么多哀号的基督徒
The black soil of Japan is filled with the wailing of so many Christians.
传教士的赤血已流淌太多
The red blood of priests has float profusely.
教堂的墙已被推倒
The walls of churches have fallen down.
我们已将生命托付此人
We have committed our lives to this man.
-主所托付者更多
-Jesus entrusted more.
来吧
Come on.
这儿，这儿
Here, here!
- 吉次郎! 你去哪儿
- Kichijiro! Where you go?
吉次郎
Kichijiro!
他要背叛我们
He is going to betray us.
吉次郎
Kichijiro!
(用拉丁语祷告)
(Praying in Latin)
你祷告得太快了
What you will do too quickly.
神父(葡萄牙语)
Padre?
快点，我们没时间了，没时间
Hurry, we have no time. No time!
这地方是哪儿
What is this place?
友義村
Tomogi
日本
Japan?
请快点
Please be quick.
这样危险看不到你
So dangers can not see you.
我很抱歉，神父
I'm sorry, Padre.
太危险了，处决尤甚以往
Too dangerous, there are more executions than ever.
如果他们知道我们是基督徒
If they know we are Christians.
我们会被杀掉
We will be killed.
上帝听到你了
The Lord hears you.
是的，他把你们派给我们
Yes. He sent you to us.
请，进来，进来
Please. Enter, enter.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我们有点吃的，如果你们愿意
We have little food. If you would like.
你们会安处此地直至早上
You will be safe here till morning.
坐吧，坐吧，请
Sit, sit, please.
我很抱歉，对不起
I'm sorry. Sorry.
你们这样怎么活
How do you live like this?
我指，你们作为基督徒怎么活
I mean, how do you live as Christians.
当危险如此之巨
When the danger is so great.
你懂吗
You understand?
我们秘密祈祷，但我们有爷爷大人(じいさま)
We pray in secret, but we have a Jiisama.
爷爷大人
Jiisama?
谁是爷爷大人
Who is the Jiisama?
你领导他们？你领导村庄
You lead them? You lead the village?
祷告？祈祷
In prayer, in devotions?
他能施行的唯一圣礼是洗礼
The only sacrament he can perform is baptism.
我们跟爷爷大人做礼拜，我们隐藏基督像
We worship with the Jiisama, we hide the Christian images.
神依旧眷顾我们？
God still sees us?
- 是吗？是的
- Yes? Yes.
即使我们没有传教士，直到现在
Even though we don't have a priest, until now.
请吃
Please eat!
谢谢你
Thank you.
在此每位基督徒都是我们秘密教会一份子
Every Christian here is part of our secret church.
这种信仰，这种信仰，你们有此信仰，如此强大
This faith, this faith, this faith you have, is so strong.
你们能有这般勇气
You have such courage.
只是这儿有此信仰，还是
It is only here that there is such faith or...
其它村庄也有
...in other villages too?
我们不知道别的村
We do not know about other villages.
我们从不去那儿
We never go there.
你们不去
You don't go?
别的村太危险了
Other villages are so dangerous.
你不知该信任谁
You do not know who to trust.
每个人都害怕奉行官
Everyone fears the Inquisitor,
井上大人
Inoue Sama.
供出基督徒
Inform on Christian,
他们给你壹佰枚银币
and they give you 100 pieces of silver.
贰佰拿基督修道士
200 for a Christian brother
拿传教士，叁佰
and for priest. 300.
叁佰
300.
我们必须去别的村
We must go to the other villages.
你必须让他们知道传教士又来这儿了
You must let them know that priests are here again.
我们又来日本这儿了
And we are here in Japan again.
会好起来的
It would be good.
传闻
There was hears
有位神父，曾在此处
a Padre, who was here
叫做费雷拉
called Ferreira.
神父费雷拉
Father Ferreira.
你听说过他吗
Have you heard of him?
象我们
Like us？
没。- 没
No. - No?
你们不吃吗
You do not eat?
这是为(感谢)你们(教导我们信仰主)准备的
It is you who feed us.
他们不敢经由大路带我们去别处
They do not dare take us anywhere by the main road.
如此潜行真是个可怕的负担
To hide like this must be a terrible burden.
我被来自这些人的珍视的感受淹没
I was overwhelmed by the love I felt from these people.
即使他们脸上并无明示
Even though their faces couldn't show it.
多年的保密，已使他们的脸成为面具
Long years of secrecy, have made their faces into masks.
为何他们非得痛苦如斯
Why do they have to suffer so much?
为何神让他们忍受这般负累
Why did God make them to bear such a burden?
这是这儿最安全的
This is the safest here.
这是做木炭的小屋
This hut for making charcoal.
- 当你听到这种声音
- When you hear this sound.
就是我们
It will be us.
如果你听到任何不一样
If you hear anything else.
藏住
Hide.
白天我们紧闭小屋门扉
During the day we keep the door of our hut tightly closed.
力求悄无声息
And refrain from the slightest noise,
以免外面路过的人听到
lest anyone passing outside may hear it.
只有天黑才可安全的下山进村
Only the dark makes it safe for us to go down into the village.
去主持信徒
And administer to the faithful.
终于，他们有了传教士可以原谅他们的罪
Finally, they had priests to forgive their sins.
赐福我，神父，我有罪啊
Bless me Padre, for I have sinned.
忏悔。- 我有罪
Confession. - I have sinned!
再来一次？
One more time?
什么？从头开始吗
What? From the beginning?
再来一次
One more time.
我们整夜聆听他们的忏悔
We heard their confessions all night.
即使我们并非总能确定告解的是什么
Even though we could not always be sure what was being confessed
现在天主教带来了爱
And now Christianity brought love，
尊严，既第一次被视为神的子民而非牲畜
The dignity for the first time of being treated like God's creatures, not animals
以及承诺，既他们所有的苦难不会以虚无终结
And the promise that all their suffering would not end in nothingness，
而是救赎
But in salvation.
我们在深夜举行弥撒
We offer mass in the dead of night.
就像他们在地下墓穴做那样
Just as they did in the catacombs.
轻声地
Quietly.
我们现在与神同在天堂了？
We now are with God in Paradiso?
- 天堂？天堂！- 是的，天堂
- Paradiso? Paradise? - Yes, paradise.
现在？- 是的
Now? - Yes.
不，不是
No, no.
但现在神就在那儿
But God is there now
- 直至永远
- and forever
他为我们大家准备了位置，即使现在
He prepares a place for us all, even now.
抱歉，塞巴斯蒂，为我的不耐烦
Sorry Sebastian for my impatience.
我为我的挫折甚感羞愧
I'm ashamed of my frustration.
孩子现已安享神的恩典，那才是重要的
The child is safe in the grace of God now, and that is what is important.
而你是个不良耶稣会士
And you're a bad Jesuit.
我厌倦了整日被困此处
I'm sick of being trapped in here all day!
吃吧
Eat.
我们甚至不知神父费雷拉是生是死
We don't even know if Father Ferreira is alive or dead.
村民们从未听说过他
The villagers never even heard of him.
这些人太担惊受怕了
These people are so frightened.
满脑子恐惧，还有虱子
There's fear over their heads and lice.
他们有我们，我们使他们安心
They have us, we comfort them.
我们还需坚持到几时
How much longer can we do that?
我们请缨这使命，弗朗西斯科
We asked for this mission, Francisco.
我们祈求此番历练，然后神听到了
We prayed for this in the exercises. God heard us then.
现在他也听着我们
And he hears us now!
那也许他能引导我们找到费雷拉，如此我们就能知道真相
Then may he guide us to Ferreira, so we can know the truth.
你觉得那可能吗？他的力量失去了
You think it's possible that his strength gave up
趴在筑后守面前，像狗一样献上膝盖
And he groveled to this Inquisitor anyway, went on his knees like a dog?
谣言就是那样
That so is the rumor.
即使井上是公认的魔鬼，费雷拉必能对抗他
Even if Inoue is the devil everyone claims, Ferreira would stand up to him.
我们俩有一个得去长崎找到他
One of us must go to Nagasaki and find him.
那太危险
It's too dangerous!
对我们，对那些庇护我们的人
For us, for the people who shelter us.
我们派吉次郎去，他带回消息我们再行动
We sent Kichijiro and he brings back word we can act on.
你疯了吗
Are you mad?
他在哪儿
Where is he?
他并不在此
He's never here.
他总是喝醉，你知他不可信
He's always drunk, you know he can't be trusted.
那咋整啊？我们总得做点啥好找到神父费雷拉
What do we do? We must do something to find Father Ferreira!
我们出去，我们冒个险，只呆一会儿
Let's go out. Let's risk it. Just for a moment.
看啦
Look.
那是神的信号
That's God's sign.
别动
Don't move.
有人在盯着我们
Someone's here watching us.
神父
Padre.
那不是暗号
That is not the signal.
- 神父
- Padre.
- 别害怕，没事的
- Do not be afraid. It's alright.
- 我们不会伤害你们
- We won't hurt you.
- 我们是基督徒，神父
- We're Christians, Padre.
- 基督徒！
- Christian!
- 我们需要你们
- We need you.
别，别
No, no.
塞巴斯蒂安！别！塞巴斯蒂安
Sebastian! No! Sebastian!
神父
Padre!
我们吓着你们，我们很抱歉
We frightened you, we are sorry.
我们想请求你们去我们村，去五岛
We want to ask you to come to our village. To Goto.
那儿的人失去其信仰，我们的孩子需要你们
People miss our faith there. Our children need you.
我们没弥撒，没忏悔
We have no mass, no confession.
我们能做的只有祷告
All we can do is pray.
你们怎知我们在这儿
How did you know we were here?
谁告诉你的
Who told you?
是个信徒吗
Did one of the faithful?
是我们村的基督徒，吉次郎
It was a Christian of our village, Kichijiro.
吉次郎
Kichijiro?
我们，我们，我们的吉次郎
Our, our, our Kichijiro?
他说他跟你们一起来这儿
He said he came here with you.
是的，但他不是基督徒
Yes, but he's not a Christian.
不，他是
Yes, he is.
是真的，他宣布背叛神
It's true, he spoke against God
向奉行官井上大人
to the Inquisitor Inoue Sama.
- 但那是八年前了
- But that was eight years ago.
- 他全家都被检验
- His whole family was put to test.
他说背叛神
He spoke against God.
但他仍相信
But he still believes.
- 不
- No.
- 他们需要传教士在五岛。不，不，神父
- They need priests on Goto. - No, no Padre.
但是茂吉，我们会回到这儿
But Mokichi we will return here.
- 不，不，神父！- 我们会回到这儿
- No, no, Padre! - We will return here.
我不认识五岛的人
I do not know the people of Goto,
因此我不知他们是否可信
So I do not know they can be trusted.
他们是基督徒，跟我们一样
These are Christians. Like us.
吉次郎叫他们来这里，我不知何故
Kichijiro told them to come here. I am not sure why.
- 他为何做这一切？- 吉次郎带我们来到友義村这儿
- Why does he do anything? - Kichijiro brought us here to Tomogi.
就只是待几天
It will only be for a few days.
但是，一人留在这儿？拜托
But one will stay here? Please.
我们正丢下他们
We're losing them.
牧師大人
神父大人
没关系的，没关系
だいじょうぶ，だいじょうぶやげ
快点
はやく
是的，是的
そうだ，そうだ
我在旅途中感受到的恐惧逐渐消失
The fear I felt on the journey faded away
因为迎接我的喜悦，几乎像我本人一样伟大
Because the joy which greeted me was almost as great as my own.
即使吉次郎看起来也是颇受欢迎
Even the sight of Kichijiro was somehow welcome.
我感谢神把我带到这里
I thanked God for bringing me here.
在那天，信徒收到了新的希望
On that day, the faithful received fresh hope.
而我重获新生
And I was renewed.
他们则奔向我
And they came to me.
不只是五岛，还有基督徒不辞路遥
Not only from Goto, for the Christians made their way
翻山越岭，从别的村来
through the mountains, from other villages.
我感觉神本尊是如此之近
I felt God himself was so near.
他们在此活得如此艰难
Their lives here were so hard.
他们生如牲畜又死如牲畜
They live like beasts and die like beasts.
但基督不是为善良和美丽而死
But Christ did not die for the good and beautiful
那太容易
That is easy enough.
难的是为悲惨和堕落而死
The hard thing is to die for the miserable and corrupt.
但在这儿，我知道我是他们中的一员
But here I knew I was one of them
我能分享到他们灵魂的饥渴
and I shared the hunger of their spirit.
又一个祷告得到回应，在五岛
Another prayer was answered on Goto.
在那儿我得到了首个真实消息
It was there I learned the first real news
某人可能知道神父费雷拉
of someone who might know Father Ferreira.
神父费雷拉
Padre Ferreira?
是的，你认识他？- 是啊
Yes, do you know him? - Yes.
你见过他？- 是啊
You've seen him? - Yes.
何时
When?
他给婴儿施了赞美
He made a praise for infant.
- 小孩。- 婴儿
- Baby. - Infant.
还有病人
And sick.
在千町
At Chimachi.
但，是在最严禁之前
But was before that Problem.
如今何在
Where is this?
靠近长崎。长崎
Near Nagasaki. Nagasaki.
我不晓得，我不晓得
I don't know, I don't know.
他们渴望获得信仰的有形之物
They are desperate for tangible signs of faith.
所以我尽我所能
So I provided what I could.
我担心他们看重这些简陋的信物
I worry they value these poor signs of faith
甚于信仰本身
more than faith itself.
但我们怎能拒绝他们
But how could we deny them?
最终，我只得把念珠分掉
And finally, I had to part with my rosary.
在五岛，我完全疲于应付
In Goto, I was completely overwhelmed.
我施洗过上百的成人和儿童
I baptized over a hundred adults and children.
聆听无数的忏悔
Heard confessions without number.
只有吉次郎的忏悔我觉得最有必要
But it was from Kichijiro that I felt the greatest need.
你没拿念珠。- 我不配
You did not take the rosary. - I did not deserve it.
为何
Why?
因为你背弃神
Because you denied God?
对
Yes.
只是为了保命
But only to live.
我们全家，奉行官逼我们放弃信仰
My whole family, the Inquisitor wanted us to give up our faith.
踩踏基督像
Stomp on Jesus,
用我们的脚
with our foot.
只需一下，即可活命
Just once, just rest.
他们不愿
But they would not.
但... 我踩了
But... I did.
而我不会背弃他们
But I could not abandon them.
即使我背弃了神
Even if I had abandoned God.
所以，我看着他们死去
So I watched them die.
无论我去哪儿，我看到烈火、闻到焦臭
Wherever I go, I see the fire and smell the flesh.
当我看到你跟神父加佩...
When I saw you and Padre Garupe...
...第一次
...for the first time,
我开始相信...
I started to believe...
...神可能要我回去
...that God might take me back.
因为在我梦里...
Because in my dreams...
...烈火不再那么明亮
...the fire was no longer so bright.
你要我听你的忏悔吗
You want me to hear your confession?
赐福我，神父
Bless me, Padre.
我有罪啊
For I have sinned.
在五岛的六天以及吉次郎的重拾信仰
Those six days at Goto and Kichijiro's renewal of faith
让我觉得吾命甚有价值
Made me feel that my life was of value
而我真的是对那些民众有用，在这个国家...
And that I could really be of use to the people in this country...
...地球的尽头
...The ends of the earth.
奉行所来人了，他们在村里
Men from the Inquisitor, they are in the village.
他们抓了市
They took Ichizo.
我们收到告发...
We've been informed...
...你们中有人...
...that some of you...
...比如这个可怜的人
...like this poor wretch here...
...是基督徒
...are Christians.
但我们年年上缴赋税...
But we pay our taxes every year...
...为藩背徭负役
...and do our duty to the State.
我们在庙里敬拜神祗
We worship Buddha in the temple.
我很清楚...
I am well aware...
...你们都是良民
...that you are all good people.
我们只要获悉...
We only want to hear about...
...那些信奉着...
...those who embrace...
...非法信仰的人...
...the outlawed faith...
...和那些...
...and those...
...窝藏他们的人...
...who hide them...
迟早，我们将会知道他们是谁
In time,we will know who they are.
想想告发的赏金
Think of the price for information.
这么多的银币
This much silver.
不要显得极害怕
Don't look so scared.
我们给他们三天时间
Let's give them three days.
松开他
Untie him.
你有三天
You have three days.
我们会放了这个人
We will let this one go.
但如果三天内我们没收到任何消息
But if we hear nothing in three days...
...除了他...
...in addition to him...
...我还要带走三个人质
...I will take three more hostages.
四个人质都会送往长崎
The four hostages will be sent to Nagasaki.
还有...
And...
...他们中的一个...
...one of them...
...必有你
...must be you.
- 不，我们不怕死，神父
- No, we are not afraid to die, Padres.
我们永不背叛您
And we will never surrender you.
- 没人该死。- 不，但是我们都危险
- No one should die. - No, but we will be in danger
无论去留
Whether you go or stay.
留下，留下，我们永不背叛您
Stay. Stay. We will never surrender you.
但他们会不断搜查，如果我们留下
But they'll keep coming if we stay.
他们会摧毁全村，杀掉你们全部，若我们躲于此
They could destroy the entire village and kill you all while we hide.
是的，我们别无选择，茂吉，只能如此
Yes, we have no choice, Mokichi, it's the only thing to do.
这样才会危险远离你们
This would draw the danger away from you.
我们可以藏在吉次郎的岛上
We can hide on Kichijiro's island.
我的岛
My island?
不，不会有差别，在那儿还是在这儿
No, there is no difference between there and here.
他们会去五岛，他们要搜查
They will come to Goto, they will search.
同样的事会发生在五岛
Same thing will happen to Goto.
他们应当离开
They should leave.
神父应当离开
The Padres should leave.
这样，我们将得救
That way, we will be saved!
你不能那样说
You can't say that!
他们来传播上帝的教诲
They came to spread Deusu's teachings!
我们不能就这么抛弃他们...
We can't just give them up...
...去遭受井上大人的酷刑，毕竟他们是为我们而为
...to Inoue-sama's tortures after all they have done for us.
他们已把我们置于险境
They've put us all in danger!
我们不至于如此遭罪，神父没来的话
We wouldn't be in such trouble had the Padres not come!
安静！安静
Be quiet! Be quiet!
我们得保护...
We will protect...
...神父
...the Padres.
你们得留下
You will stay.
现在我们必须挑两人加入我们
Now we must pick two more to join us.
我，茂吉和另两个人质
Me, Mokichi and two more hostages.
谁愿加入我跟茂吉...
Who will join me and Mokichi...
...成为人质去荣耀上帝
...and become a hostage to honor Deusu?
吉次郎不是这儿的
Kichijiro's not from here.
为何不选他
Why not him?
是啊
Yes.
为我们所有人着想，你愿去吗
For all our sakes, would you go?
官差不会太为难你
The officials won't be so hard on you.
他们只抓友義村的人
It's the people of Tomogi they want.
他不是这儿的
He's not from here.
他可能就是告发我们的人
He could be the one who informed on us.
我不是告发者
I'm not an informer!
神父，告诉他们
Padre, tell them!
我不是告发者
I'm not an informer!
我告解过我全部的罪行
I confessed all my sins!
那如果你收到了上帝的祝福...
Then if you've received the Lord's blessing...
...实行之
...act like it.
荣耀他，用你的命
Honor Him with your life.
说得对
That's right!
荣耀？你说的是什么啊
Honor? What are you talking about?
真正的基督徒会懂
A real Kirishitan would know!
我要捣碎你的头
I'm going to smash your head!
求你
Please!
替我们去吧
Go in our place.
求你
Please.
神父
Padre.
但是神父
But Padre?
如果我们被迫去踏踩圣像
If we are forced to trample on the Lord,
我想照做
I want that for me.
你必须祈祷以获勇气，茂吉
You must pray for courage, Mokichi.
但如果我们不做他们要求的
But if we do not do what they want,
本村的每个人都会有危险
There can be danger for everyone in the village.
他们会入狱
They can put in prison.
永远出不来
They can wait forever.
我们该咋办
What should we do?
踏踩
Trample.
那就踏踩吧
It's alright to trample.
你在说啥？
What are you saying?
你不能
You can't!
- 茂吉，你不能
- Mokichi. You can't.
我做了这个给爷爷大人
I made this for the Jiisama.
它是我们的全部，直到你们来了
It was all we had, until you came.
收下这个，请
Take this, please.
以主之名
In Jesus' name.
你的信念给了我力量，茂吉
Your faith gives me strength, Mokichi.
我希望，我能以同样多的给你
I wish, I could give as much to you.
我对神的爱很强烈
My love for God is strong.
那跟信念一样吗
Could that be the same as faith?
是的
Yes.
是的，肯定是的
Yes. It must be.
这些人是地球上最虔诚的神的生物
These people are the most devoted of God's creatures on Earth.
神父范礼安我告解，我开始怀疑
Father Valignano I confess, I began to wonder.
神予我们考验以测试我们，而他所做一切都是好的
God sends us trials to test us and everything he does is good.
我祈祷能像主之子那样接受考验
And I prayed to undergo trials like his son.
但为何一定要他们的考验如此可怕
But why must their trial be so terrible?
且为何，当我看着自己的心
And why, when I look in my own heart.
我给他们的答复显得那么软弱吗
Do the answers I give them seem so weak?
踩(踏む)
Fume.
所有人都做了他们所命令的
All of them did as they were commanded.
但那还不够
But it was not enough.
你以为我们极易被愚弄
You think we're fooled so easily?
我们有注意...
We noticed...
...你的呼吸如何...
...how your breathing...
...马上变沉重
...turned heavy just now.
那不可能
That can't be!
因为我们是佛教徒
Because we are Buddhists.
很好
Fine.
我们试下另一个方式
Let's try this another way.
吐这个...
Spit on this...
...然后说...
...and then say...
...你们所谓的圣洁的处女...
...your so-called Blessed Blessed Virgin...
...是妓女
...is a whore.
你是基督徒
You are a Christian.
你也是基督徒
You are also a Christian.
老市不愿吐
Old Ichizo would not do it.
茂吉没吐
Mokichi could not.
只有吉次郎吐了，余下没做
But Kichijiro succeeded where the rest failed.
我必须相信他同遭痛苦，有如别人
I must believe he suffered along with the others.
你也是基督徒
You are a Christian, too.
他们都是...
They are all...
...基督徒
...Christians.
带走他们
Seize them!
他们被给了米酒
They were given Sake.
像罗马士兵把醋给垂死的基督
As the Roman soldier offered vinegar to the dying Christ.
我祈祷，他们记得我们主的痛苦
I prayed, they remembered our Lord's suffering.
并获得勇气及安慰于此
And took courage and comfort from it.
上帝(拉丁语)
Deus.
上帝
Deus!
天堂
Paradiso.
上帝大人
Deus-sama.
请收下爷爷大人的灵魂
Please receive Jiisama's spirit.
爷爷大人的苦难结束了
Jiisama's suffering has ended.
收下他，主啊
Receive him, Lord.
主啊
Lord!
以您的荣耀
In Your glory.
求您...耶稣啊
Please... Jesus!
这使得茂吉四天才死
It took Mokichi four days to die.
临终，他唱了赞美诗。他的歌喉是那唯一的声音
At the end he sang a hymn. His voice was the only sound.
村民聚集在海滩上，始终沉默着
The people of the village, who would gather on the beach, were always silent.
他们被严密看守，所以遗体不能进行...
The people were watched closly, so the bodies could not be given...
天主教的葬礼
a Christian burial.
茂吉的遗体浸水太多使火焰燃起浓烟
Mokichi's body was so heavy with water it turned the flames to smoke.
在最终烧着之前
Before it finally caught fire.
烧剩的遗骨被抛入大海，这样他们就得不到祭拜
Any bones that remained were scattered in the ocean, so they could not be venerated.
神父范礼安，你会说他们的死不无意义
Father Valignano, you will say that their death is not meaningless.
当然了，神听到了他们的祷告，当他们逝去之时
Surely, God heard their prayers as they died.
但他听到他们的痛嚎吗
But did he hear their screams?
我该如何解释他的沉默，对这些人，已忍受如此之多者
How can I explain his silence to these people, who have endured so much?
我得竭尽全力去理解这些，亲自去
I need all my strength to understand it myself.
这可能是我最后一次向您汇报，神父
This may be my last report to you, Father.
今天我们得知差卒，上山搜寻我们
Today we hear the guards, are in the mountains looking for us.
所以我们决定：要安全需分开
So we have decided it would be safer to separate.
- 所以你才对？
- So you were right?
- 如果我们离开，他们还能活命
- If we left, they might still be alive.
别说那些，那不是真的！我们不用怀疑，留下会要我们的命
Don't say that, that is not true! And we can not doubt. That will be our death.
- 我们放弃了？就干这些？我们就会跑路？
- Are we giving up? Is that what we're doing? Are we running away?
不！- 在他们已为我们而死之后？
No! - After the people have died for us?
他们不是为我们而亡！加佩，他们没有为我们而死
They did not die for us! Garupe, they did not die for us!
- 我感觉象个懦夫
- I feel like a coward.
我的爱永远与你同在。- 我祈祷能坚强如你
My love is always with you. - I pray to be as strong as you.
神父加佩将去平户继续使命
Father Garupe will make for Hirado to continue the mission,
(注：平户，日本最古老天主教会所在地)
而我则重返五岛
and I will return to Goto.
弗朗西斯科！要活着
Francisco! Stay alive.
要活着
Stay alive!
神父，我请求原谅我的软弱和怀疑
Father, I ask forgiveness for my weakness and my doubt.
我还恳请您记得
And I ask you to remember
神父加佩跟我有您的慈悲有您的祷告
Father Garupe and me in your mercies and in your prayers.
您忠诚的孩子
Your obedient son.
我想像着您的儿子
I imagine your son.
钉到十字架上
Nailed to the cross.
我嘴有如尝醋
My mouth tastes like vinegar.
那是五岛吗
Is that Goto?
天父，赞您之名
Father in Heaven praised be thy name.
我就是一个带来灾难的外国人
I'm just a foreigner who brought disaster.
那就是他们现在所认为的我
That's what they think of me now.
我现在梦到了圣·弗朗西斯·泽维尔
I dream of now Saint Francis.
他在这里找到的所有光荣的可能性发生了什么？
What happened to all the glorious possibility he found here?
我为基督做了什么
What have I done for Christ?
我为基督做着什么
What am I doing for Christ?
我为基督将做什么
What will I do for Christ?
我感到强烈的诱惑，我感到绝望的强烈诱惑
I feel so tempted. I feel so tempted to despair.
我很害怕
I'm afraid.
等待的你的沉默是可怕的
The wait of your silence is terrible.
我祷告但我已迷失
I pray but I'm lost.
莫非我只是向虚无祷告？
Or am I just praying to nothing?
虚无
Nothing.
因为您不在那儿
Because you're not there.
我祈祷您的宽恕
I pray for your forgiveness.
如果我的报告突然结束
If my report now comes to an abrupt end,
别以为我们死了
do not think that we are dead.
因为如果加佩和我死了，日本教会与我们同亡
For if Garupe and I die, the Japanese Church dies with us.
我以为我被跟踪了。你还好吗？神父
I thought I was being followed. Are you alright, Padre?
抱歉
Sorry.
神父
Padre?
为何你要回到这儿？神父
Why did you come back here, Padre?
这地方危险
This place is dangerous.
我们必须小心
We must be careful.
悬赏叁佰个银币拿你
There is a prize of 300 pieces of silver for you.
叁佰
300.
犹大只得叁拾
Judas got only 30.
有基督徒在别的村
There are Christians in another villages...
并不远
Not far
我们可以藏那儿，我会照顾你
We can hide there. I will take care of you.
拿去，请
Take it. Please.
你肯定很饿
You must be so hungry.
茂吉和我的家人很坚强，我太软弱
Mokichi and my family stayed strong. I am so weak.
你吗？你显然能照顾好你自己
Are you? You can certainly look after yourself.
不要自私
Not to be selfish.
我跟你不一样
I’m not like you.
我已无处可去
I have nowhere else to go.
何处可容弱者
Where is the place for a weak man?
置身如此世道
In a world like this.
你想为茂吉和市告解吗
You want to confess for Mokichi and Ichizo?
“你想做什么，快去做。”
"What you will do, do quickly."
(注：《约翰福音》13:27)
您儿子对犹大所说的话，于最后的晚餐时
Your son's words to Judas at the Last Supper.
他愤怒吗？当他说出它们
Was he angry, when he said them?
还是它们源自慈悲
Or did they come from love?
你没事吧？神父
Are you alright, Padre?
- 你看上去很累。- 我没事
- You seem so tired. - I'm alright.
你给我那鱼太咸
That fish you gave me was so salty.
我口渴
I'm thirsty!
- 什么？- 口渴
- What? - Thirst!
我们的主说过那话
Our Lord said that.
我取些水。
I get some water.
吉次郎
Kichijiro!
我取水
I get water!
吉次郎
Kichijiro!
- 抱歉，我掉了水，神父
- Sorry, I dropped the water, Padre.
我以为有什么问题
I thought something was wrong.
但是别担心
But never mind,
有条河在附近
there is a stream nearby.
你喜欢喝多少就喝多少
You can drink as much as you like.
这儿
Here.
神父！原谅我
Padre! Forgive me!
神父
Padre!
我祈祷神的宽恕
I pray for God's forgiveness!
他会宽恕吗？甚至是我
Will he forgive? Even me?
神的保佑
Blessed be God.
啥是...你名字是啥
What is...what is your name?
莫尼加
Monica.
啊，跟奥古斯丁母亲一样
Ah, like the mother of Augustine?
(注：圣·奥古斯丁 天主教圣师，奥斯定会的发起人，公元354－430)
我的受洗名
My Baptismal name.
这男子是约翰
This man is Juan.
(注：Juan，西班牙语)
他希望他的名字跟我们的传教士一样，约翰，逝者
He wanted his name to be like our priest, Juan, who died.
在云仙
At Unzen
将会有更多的人步其后尘
There will be many more joining him.
你明白吗
You understand?
为何你要那样看着我
Why you are looking at me like that?
为何你如此平静
Why are you so calm?
我们全都会死
We are all about to die!
受酷刑
Like that.
抱歉
Sorry.
我很抱歉，谢谢你
I'm sorry. Thank you.
谢谢你的食物
Thank you for the food.
谢谢您
ありがとうございます
但是神父
But Padre?
我们的神父
Our Father,
神父约翰...
Padre Juan...
...说过如果我们死了...
...said if we die...
...我们会上天堂
...we will go to Paradiso?
天堂
Paradise.
是的，是那样
Yes, that's right.
死了不好吗
Isn't it good to die?
天堂是如此的好过此处
Paradiso is so much better than here.
没人挨饿
No one hungry.
从不生病
Never sick.
没有杂税
No taxes.
没有重活
No hard work.
是的，当然
Yes, of course.
神父约翰
Padre Juan,
是对的
was right
...没有重活...
...there is no hard work...
...在天堂里
...in Paradiso.
根本不工作
No work at all.
没有杂税
There is no taxes.
没有苦难
There is no suffering.
我们都将同神在一起
We all will be united with God.
那里不会有痛苦
There will be no pain.
本字幕由dottob制作，不足之处敬请海涵指正。谢谢！20170207-0217
我希望你们别再给我太多麻烦了
I wish you would stop causing me so much trouble.
拜托
Please.
我们这岁数...
At our age...
...我们不该走那么远，在这大热天
...we shouldn't be traveling so far in this heat.
而灰尘...
And the dust...
今年更糟
Especially bad this year.
这一切都没必要
And it's all so unnecessary.
只需用一点功夫...
Just make a little effort...
...即可明白我们的意图
...to understand our point of view.
我们不恨你们
We don't hate you.
你们自己背上麻烦
You've brought it on yourselves.
你们也能...
And you can...
...自己摆脱它
...rid yourselves of it too.
没必要感到迷惑
No need to feel lost.
我会给你们时间想个明白
I'll give you time to think it over.
然后你们能给我个明理的答复
Then you can give me a reasonable answer.
带走
Go.
不，不是你
No, not you.
你留下
You stay!
你理解，我对他们说的吗
You understood, what I was saying to them?
你的日语够好吗
Your Japanese is good enough?
我看到你的眼睛
I saw your eyes.
什么？你以为你从那儿看到了什么
What? And what did you think you saw there?
他们是傻瓜，农民
They are fools, the peasants.
主啊，赦免他们的苦难，以您之手护其平安
Lord, spare them suffering and keep them safe in your hand.
他们能跟人高谈阔论不休却决断全无
They can talk a man down south without end and decide nothing!
但是你明白，不是吗？
But you understand, don't you?
直接说你啥意思
Just say what you mean.
这一切全取决于你...
That it all depends on you...
...他们是否获释
...whether they are set free.
如果你只说一个词
If you say just one single word,
...示范他们，否定你的信仰
...show them, deny your faith.
所以若我拒绝，你杀了我
So what if I refuse, you kill me?
殉道者之血乃教会之种苗
The blood of martyrs is the seed of the Church.
有如那些传教士...
Just like the priests...
...你屠杀于大村、长崎的
...you slaughtered in Omora, Nagasaki.
- 我们从错误中学到了
- We learned from our mistake.
处决传教士及处死农民让事情更糟
Killing the priests and killing the peasants makes it worse.
若他们能为神而死...
If they can die for their God...
...他们只会认为这能使他们更坚强
...they think it only makes them stronger.
若你觉得有必要惩罚某人，单独惩罚我
If you feel you must punish someone, punish me alone!
你！说得不像是个好传教士
You! Do not speak like a good priest.
如果你是真实的男人
If you are a real man
真正好的传教士
a truly good priest.
你应该同情基督徒
You should feel pity for the Christian.
不该那样吗？神父，不该那样吗
Isn't that so, Padre, isn't that so?
你荣耀的代价，是他们的苦难
The price for your glory is their suffering.
- 神父？
- Padre?
- 赞美神，吾等之父
- Praise be to God our Father.
赞美他
Praise be to Him.
葡萄牙语是个礼物...
The Portuguese language was a gift...
...来自你们的神父卡布拉尔
...of your Father Cabral.
我被派做你的翻译
I've been asked to interpret on your behalf.
考虑到我们可能需要你证词的一些微妙之处
There was concern that we might need certain subtleties in your testimony,
如果你被告知只能说日语
if you were told to speak only in Japanese.
证词？我...
The testimony, I...
我们希望它是公平的
We want it to be fair.
且我们已更好地掌握你们的语言...
and we'd have a better grasp of your language
...胜过你们掌握我们的
...than you do of ours.
神父卡布拉尔从未说过比“感谢神”更多
Father Cabral never managed much more than "Arigataya".
Arigataya[ありがたや]，词汇原意指罕见的事。有好事发生时，当对神说这话。值得庆幸之意
他住这儿的日子
All the time he lived here.
他只教不学
He taught, but would not learn.
他鄙视我们的语言、我们的食物、我们的习惯
He despised our language, our food, our customs.
我跟他不一样，我不像卡布拉尔
I'm not like him, I'm not like Cabral.
- 真的？- 是的
- Really? - Yes.
我们有自己的宗教信仰，神父
We have our own religion, Padre.
可惜你没有注意到它
Pity you did not notice it.
不，不
No, no.
我们只是思考的方式不同
We just think a different way.
真的
True.
你相信我们的佛只是凡人
You believe our Buddhas are only men.
只是人类
Just human beings.
即使佛，也会死
Even a Buddha dies.
跟所有人一样，他...
Like all men, he is...
...不是造物主。- 你不懂
...not the creator. - You are ignorant!
神父，只有基督徒把佛看得如凡人简单
Padre, only a Christian would see Buddha simply as a man.
我们的佛是存在的
Our Buddha is a being.
此乃人可以成为比其本身更伟大者
Which men can become something greater than himself.
若他能克服其一切妄念
If he can overcome all his illusions.
但你坚持你的妄念...
But you cling to your illusions...
...还称之为信仰
...and call them faith.
不，你不懂
No, you don't understand.
任何人只要遵从神的嘱咐
If any man follows God's commandments.
他就能过上平静快乐的生活
Then he can live a peaceful and joyous life!
我懂！我明白
I do! I do understand.
神父，这太简单了
Padre, it is perfectly simple!
"Korobu."
転ぶ
你听过那词吗
Have you heard that word?
"Korobu."
転ぶ
它意思是塌下，放弃
It means fall down. Surrender.
放弃信仰，弃教，如你所说
Give up the faith, apostatize, as you say.
做吧
Do it.
如果你不弃教
If you don't apostatize.
囚犯们会被挂起“穴吊”
The prisoners will be hang over the Pit.
直到你弃教，你们的命随血流，
Until you do, your life's bleeding away,
...一滴连一滴
...drop by drop.
有些持续几天，有些不行
Some last for days, some do not.
他们死了
They die.
他们折磨神父斯伯罗和卡索拉
They tortured Father Sporo and Kasora.
穴吊
Over the Pit.
你听说过他们吗
Have you heard of them?
还有个叫神父图姆
There was one called Pedro Tomb.
还有费雷拉，当然
And Ferreira, of course.
费雷拉
Ferreira?
你认识他
Did you knew him?
我听过他
I've heard of him.
毫无疑问，他现在在全日本都很有名
No doubt, he's well-known all over Japan now.
“有着日本名及日本妻的传教士。”
"The Priest with a Japanese name and a Japanese wife."
我不信。- 你可问任何人
I don't believe. - You can ask anyone.
长崎的人提到他就惊叹
People in Nagasaki point him out and marvel.
他如今身份很高
He is helding great steam now.
这就是为何，我相信他首先会来这儿
Which is why，I believe he came here in the first place.
傲慢的人。像他们所有人
Arrogant man. Like all of them.
这意味着他最终会屈服
Which means he'll eventually fall.
我以为殉教会成为我的救赎
I thought that martyrdom would be my salvation.
恳求神。别让它成为我的耻辱
Please God. Do not let it be my shame.
看啦！他好高
Look! He's so big!
为何你要跟着我
Why are you following me?
别跟着我
Stop following me!
感谢主，赐予温和的日子于此处
Thank you Lord for the gentle days here.
- 主教导我要爱每个人
- Jesus taught me to love everyone.
- 但我不能感到爱，对那些
- But I can not feel love to those who
- 把我们的朋友折磨致死的人
- torture our friends to death.
- 我愤怒，我不能爱他们
- I am angry. I can not love them.
连卫兵都被你的手碰过，主
Even the guards have been touched by your hand, Lord.
- 我感到有罪
- I feel guilty.
我想知道是否这连日的平静已证明
I wonder if this unbroken peace is proof...
- 我的死不远了
- That my death is not far away.
永不动摇
Shall never be shaken.
我看到您儿子的命运，如此清晰，有如我自己的
I see the life of your son so clearly, almost like my own.
还有他的脸
And his face...
它带走了我的所有恐惧
it takes all fear from me.
它就是那张我儿时便记得的脸
It is the face that I remember from childhood.
对我说着话
Speaking to me.
我确信这点
I'm sure of it.
承诺着我不会放弃你
Promising I will not abandon you.
我不会放弃你
I will not abandon you.
穿上它们
Put them on.
你该感到荣幸，这是我们的传教士(指和尚)穿的
You should be honored, it is what our priests wear.
神父罗德里格斯，来自葡萄牙，是吗
Padre Rodriguez from Portugal, yes?
我很抱歉，神父，为我说的话
I am sorry, Padre, for my speaking.
我的语言不太好
My language is not so good
...但是藩主...
...but His Lordship...
...筑后奉行...
...the governor of Chikuwo...
...担心关于...
...is anxious about...
...你的...适...适应...
...Your are com...comfort...
...适应
...Comfort.
- 也许不适应
- Perhaps discomfort.
不适应，是的
Discomfort, yes.
关于你为何到此
About why you are here
如果你不自在
and if you are not at ease
请说出来
please say so.
你旅途遥远
Your trip was long.
危险众多
There were many dangers.
你决心的力量极大的触动了我们
The power of your determination touches us greatly.
我们知你已受苦甚巨
We know you have already suffered greatly.
我们不希望再增你的苦难
We do not wish to add to your suffering.
即使我们可能这样做
And the thought that we might do so
...也使我们痛苦
...is painful for us too.
谢谢
Thank you.
神父
Padre.
你带来的教义...
The doctrine you bring with you...
...在西班牙和葡萄牙可能是真的
...may be true in Spain and Portugal.
但我们仔细研究过
But we have studied it carefully.
专心致志，积日累久
So devotedly over much time.
我们发现它在日本毫无用处，没有价值
We find it is of no use and no value in Japan.
我们断定它是危险之物
We have concluded that it is a danger.
但我们相信，我们给你们带来了真理
But we believe, we have brought you the truth.
而真理是普遍的
And the truth is universal.
它对任何国家都是共同的，在任何时候。这就是为何我们称之为真理
It's common to all countries, at all times. That's why we call it the truth.
如果教义在日本这儿不像在葡萄牙那么正确
If a doctrine weren't as true here in Japan, as it is in Portugal.
那么我们就不会称之为真理
Then we couldn't call it the truth.
我看出你不用你的双手工作，神父
I see that you do not work with your hands, Father.
但人人皆知，一棵树在某地茂盛茁壮
But everyone knows a tree which flourishes in one kind of earth.
在别处可能腐烂死亡
May decay and die in another.
这与天主教的树是一样的，叶烂于此
It is the same with the tree of Christianity. The leaves decay here.
芽遂亡
The buds die.
不是土壤杀死了芽
It is not the soil that has killed the buds.
有叁拾万基督徒在日本这儿，在土壤...
There were 300.000 Christians here in Japan, before the soil was...
怎样
Yes?
...中毒前
...was poisoned.
你没有回复吗？
You have no reply?
你又何必？你永远不必去改变我的心
Why should you? You're never going to change my heart.
这就有如，我不必去改变你的
And it seems like, I'm not going to change yours.
你想测试我的信仰？给我一个真正的挑战
You want to test my faith? Give me a real challenge!
带我去见奉行官
Bring me to the Inquisitor!
带我...
Bring me...
...去见井上大人
...to Inoue Sama!
为何他们要笑？
Why are they laughing?
我没说任何好笑的，为何他们要笑
I didn't say anything funny, why are they laughing?
因为，神父...
Because Padre...
因为
Because.
我就是筑后国的筑后守(官职名)
I am the governor of Chikuwo.
我就是奉行官
I am the Inquisitor.
我是，你知道吗
I am, you know it?
多久？他们得这样干多久？在雨中
How long? How long will they have to work like this in the rain?
直到完工
Until finished.
- 神父！
- Padre!
- 神父
请听我说
Please listen to me!
他们威胁我
They threatened me.
- 我从没拿过他们的钱
- I never took their money!
我没有为钱出卖你
I did not betray you for money!
小心他，神父
Be careful with him, Padre.
可能井上大人雇他使我们踏踩
Maybe Inoue Sama pays him to make us trample.
- 不！他没有
- No, he did not!
恳求神父，让我告解
Please Padre, let me confess.
- 神父
- Padre.
我知，我闻到了，我闻到了罪
I know, I smell. I smell of sin.
我想再次告解，主就会把我洗干净
I want to confess again, so the Lord can wash me clean.
为何你要来这儿？
Why did you come here?
这是为赎罪吗？
Is it for absolution?
你有任何赎罪是啥的认识吗？
Do you have any understanding what absolution is?
你懂我正在说什么吗？
Do you understand what I've been saying?
多年前，我可能会死为一个好基督徒
Years ago, I could have died a good Christian.
没有迫害
There was no persecution.
为何我生在现在？
Why was I born now?
这太不公平
This is so unfair!
对不起
I am sorry.
你还相信吗
Do you still believe?
赐福我神父，我有罪啊
Bless me Padre. For I have sinned.
我惭愧，因如此软弱
I am sorry for being so weak.
我惭愧，这已经发生了
I am sorry, this has happened.
我惭愧，因我对你所做的一切
I am sorry for what I did to you!
救救我，神父
Help me, Padre.
解除此罪
Take away the sin.
我会再次尝试要坚强
I will try again to be strong.
天父，耶稣怎会爱一个卑鄙如此的人
Father, how could Jesus love a wretch like this?
这里到处都是邪恶，我感觉到它的力量，甚至它的美丽
There is evil all around in this place, I sense its strength even its beauty.
但这个男人两者皆无
But there is none of that in this man.
他不配称为邪恶
He is not worthy to be called evil.
安心去吧
Go in peace.
我觉得.. 我，我害怕.. 耶稣，原谅我
I feel.. I, I fear.. Jesus, forgive me.
我也许不值得您爱
I may not be worthy of you.
这只是个形式
This is just a formality.
只要一步就行
Just one step will do.
我们不要求你真诚地去做
We're not asking you to do it sincerely.
只须把你的脚放这东西上，不用背叛你的信仰
Just putting your foot on the thing won't betray your faith.
我不会真的关心
I don't really care.
你越早做...
The sooner you do it...
...我们就越快避开太阳
...the sooner we get out of the sun.
只需用你的脚轻轻地踩，若你愿意
Just touch it with your foot lightly if you like.
不管你愿意几何...
However you like...
...你将会立即获释
...and you'll be free immediately.
它只是图片
It's only a picture.
把你脚放其上
Put your foot on it.
马上
Now!
下一个
Next!
你怎么样？
How about you?
这绝无意义
It is pointless.
马上
Now!
下一个
Next!
你可以轻轻地做
You can do it lightly.
然后你就自由了
Then you will be free.
马上
Now.
只需踏上它
Just step on it.
前进
Go ahead.
下一个
Next.
只一步
Only one step.
马上...
Now...
你肯定想获释
You must want to be free.
获释
Be free!
把你脚放其上
Put your foot on it!
都带他们回去
Take them all back.
留下那个
Leave that one behind.
谢谢主听到我的祈祷
Thank you Lord for hearing my prayer!
这就是基督徒的下场
This is what happens to Christians!
但是...
But...
...我将向你们示范，一个如何避免那种命运的例子
...I will show you an example of how to avoid that fate.
带他过来
Bring him here.
前进
Go ahead.
把脚放上去
Just put your foot there.
看看这有多容易
See how easy it is?
我承认他练习过
I admit he's had practice.
但看看这动作多简单
But look how simple the movement is.
它甚至没有鞠躬难
It is not even as hard as bowing.
不是吗
Is it not?
或跑步
Or running.
马上滚
Now go!
滚出去
Get out of here!
你们看见了吗
You see?
他履行了他的义务
He lived up to his obligation.
就这样
That is all.
我很抱歉，如今我已忽略你多日，神父
I'm sorry I've neglected you for some days now, Padre.
我在平户有些事
But I had business in Hirado.
我希望有天你能亲自去那儿
I hope you get to go there yourself sometime.
那里确实很漂亮
Sure it's very beautiful.
传闻有个有趣故事，关于统治那儿的大名
There lays an interesting story about the Dimeov who ruled there
他有四个侧室
He had four concubines.
四个
Four.
她们都漂亮，但她们...
They were all beautiful, but they...
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
也许这故事不应说与独身的传教士
Maybe this is not a story for a celibate priest.
没关系，请继续
It's alright, please go on.
那种情况下，大名的侧室都嫉妒
In that case, the Dimeov's concubines were all jealous.
她们斗来斗去没完没了
And they fought and fought without end,
于是平户大名赶她们出其城
so the Dimeov Hirado drove them away from his castle.
安宁就再次来到他的生活
And peace came into his life again.
你认为这故事有教训吗？
Do you think this story has a lesson?
是的
Yes.
即这是个很明智的男人
That this was a very wise man.
我很高兴，那意味着你明白大名就像日本
I'm glad. That means you understand the Dimeov is like Japan.
那些侧室是西班牙，葡萄牙，荷兰，英格兰
And these concubines are Spain, Portugal, Holland, England.
人人试图获得相对别人的优势
Each trying to gain advantage against the other
还在过程中摧毁了房子
and destroy the house in the process.
既然你说此人聪明，你就会明白
Since you said this man is wise, you will understand
...为何我们必须禁止天主教
...why we must outlaw the Christians.
然而，我们的教会教导一夫一妻
Well. Our Church teaches monogamy.
一个妻子
One wife.
那如果日本在四人中选一个合法的妻子呢？
What if Japan were to choose one lawful wife from the four?
你指葡萄牙
You mean Portugal?
不
No.
我指神圣的教堂
I mean the Holy Church.
难道你不认为这样好多了，男人忘记外国女人...
Don't you think it would be better for the man to forget about foreign women...
...选一个他本国的
...and choose one of his own?
国籍并不那么重要，当婚姻已至
Nationality is not so important when it comes to a marriage.
...重要的是爱
...what matters is love.
爱和忠诚
Love and fidelity.
爱！
Love!
神父，也有男人被困扰于
Padre, there are men who are plagued
...丑女的痴情
...by the persistent love of an ugly woman.
这就是传教工作对你的意义吗
Is that what missionary work is to you?
丑女？
An ugly woman?
好吧
Well.
是的
Yes.
你们怎么称呼一个不能生孩子的女人
How do you call a woman who cannot bear children?
不育
Barren.
不育之女不能成为真正的妻子
A barren woman can not be a true wife.
如果福音在此迷失方向，那不是教会的错
If the gospel has lost its way here, it is not the fault of the Church.
错在那些强行把忠诚从其信仰拉开者
It is the fault of those who tear away the faithful from their faith,
就像丈夫从妻子
like a husband from a wife.
你指...
You mean...
...我
...Me?
神父，你们传教士似乎不懂日本
Padre, your missionaries do not seem to know Japan!
而你，尊敬的奉行官，似乎不懂天主教
And you, Honorable Inquisitor, do not seem to know Christianity.
有些人认为你们的宗教是诅咒
There are those who think of your religion as a curse.
我不
I do not.
我懂它。从别的角度，但依然危险
I see it. In another way, but still dangerous.
我想让你想想丑女的痴情
I'd like for you to think about the persistent love of an ugly woman.
及不育之女如何绝不能当妻子
And how a barren woman should never be a wife.
神父！神父！
Padre! Padre!
神父！救救我！神父
Padre! Help me! Padre!
你们要带她们去那儿
Where are you taking them?
神父！神父
Padre! Padre!
你今天要出行
You are traveling today.
坐下，这对你更好，我认为
Sit down. It's better for you, I think.
请
Please.
神父
Padre.
你今天感觉如何
How are you feeling today?
我确信空气肯定感觉不错
I'm sure the air must feel good.
即使你是在我们的最新监狱
Even though you were in our newest prison.
旧监狱对神父们甚为艰苦
The old prison was very tough on the Padres.
雨，风及各方面
Rain, wind and every sort.
抱歉，对不起
Sorry, excuse me.
井上大人几时到此
When will Inoue Sama be here?
噢！他今天不会来
Oh! He's not coming today.
你想他吗
Do you miss him?
他对我和蔼。一日三餐
He treats me kindly. Three meals a day.
这样我的身体就会背叛我的心
So that my body will betray my heart.
这是你们的计划，不是吗
It's your plan, isn't it?
- 那就是你在等待的。- 根本不是
- That's what you're waiting for. - Not at all!
不是
No?
但今天我们在等某人
But we are waiting for someone today.
井上大人想你见见他
Inoue Sama wants you to meet him.
他随时都会到此
He will be here any moment.
他是葡萄牙人，如你本人
He's Portuguese, like yourself.
你们应该有很多话要谈
You should have a lot to talk about.
费雷拉
Ferreira?
他是你所期望的吗
Is it who you expected?
我想跟他谈。- 不忙
- I want to talk to him. - There's no hurry.
还早。有的是时间
It is early. Plenty of time.
告诉我，他知道我在这里吗
Tell me. Does he know I'm here?
我不能告诉你，我不能谈论奉行所的事
I can not tell you. I must not speak about the business of the Inquisitor's office.
但是，我能告诉你，他知道你活着
But, I can tell you, he knows you are alive.
因为我们告诉他你弃教了
Because we told him you apostatized.
现在，你知他们用那些草席干啥吗？
Now, do you know what they use those mats for?
不
No.
看，守卫，他会对神父加佩说啥呢
Look, the guard. What could he be saying to Father Garupe?
- 记住这个，“如果你真是基督徒，你会弃教...
- Remember this, "If you are truly a Christian, you will apostatize...
...而不是让他们死。”
...and not let them die."
你知的，奉行官承诺，如果神父加佩弃教
You know. The Inquisitor promises that if Father Garupe apostatizes.
四人就会获释
The four will be free.
我希望神父加佩同意
I hope Father Garupe agrees.
我应该告诉你
I should tell you.
这些基督徒已踏踩及否认其信仰
These Christians already trampled and denied their faith.
在奉行所
At the Inquisitor's office.
如果他们做了你想要的，就让他们走
If they did what you wanted, then let them go!
让他们走！他们做了你想要的！所以让他们走！
Let them go! They did what you wanted! So let them go!
拜托！拜托！拜托！让他们走！
Please! Please! Please! Let them go!
我们不想要他们。
We don't want them.
四农民吗？
Four farmers?
海岸边的岛屿上仍有数百名天主教农民
There are still hundreds of Christian peasants
在海岸边的岛屿上
on the islands off the coast.
我们希望神父去否认
We want the Padre to deny
及做他们的榜样
and be an example to them.
- 神啊求求您
- God please!
弃教，弃教
Apostatize, Apostatize.
为他们着想，主
For their sake, Lord.
别将此留予我们
Do not leave this to us.
- 求求您
- Please!
不
No!
不，不加佩，不
No, no Garupe, no!
不，不，不，不，不，不
No, no, no, no, no, no.
- 不
- No!
不！求求您！求求您
No! Please! Please!
可怕的事，可怕的
Terrible business. Terrible.
无论你目睹它多少次
No matter how many times you see it.
想想这苦难...
Think about the suffering...
...你给这些人所造成的
...You have inflicted on these people!
只因你自私的梦想...
Just because of your selfish dream of...
...一个基督徒的日本
...a Christian Japan.
你的上帝惩罚日本...
Your Deus punishes Japan...
...通过你
...through you!
至少加佩是干净的
At least Garupe was clean,
但你
but you!
你毫无决心
You have no will.
你不配被称为传教士
You do not deserve to be called a priest.
亲爱的神，亲爱的神，你为何抛弃我
Dear God, dear God, why have you forsaken me?
你为何抛弃我
Why have you forsaken me?
我是您的儿子
I was your son.
您走上十字架的儿子
Your son who went up to the cross.
所给予他的沉默
The silent given to him.
有此岛残酷吗？沉默
Is this island cold? Silent?
噢，不，不
Oh, no, no.
可笑的？可笑的！
Ludicrous? Ludicrous!
愚蠢的？
Stupid?
愚蠢的！
Stupid!
他不会回复的
He's not going to answer.
你要我让你进去吗
Do you want me to let you in?
迟早
In time.
神父
Padre.
Padre!
来吧，神父
Come along, Padre.
我们传教士(指和尚)不喜欢你们传教士
Our priests do not like your priests,
但你仍能在此找到很多意义
but you will still find much of value here.
这是什么呢？神父
What is it, Padre?
香
The incense?
肉的气息
The smell of meat?
你吃过肉吗，自从你来到日本
Have you had any meat, since you came to Japan?
我不太喜欢自己的气味
I don't much like the smell myself.
你还没猜到？
Have you guessed yet?
你猜到谁要来吗？
Have you guessed who's coming?
这是井上大人的命令
This is Inoue Sama's command.
也是那人的愿望
And the others wish.
那人
The other?
- 神父，想想你能拯救的灵魂
- Padre, think of the souls you can save.
- 神父费雷拉
- Padre Ferreira
- 封住那儿
- Hold there!
神.. 神父
Fa.. Father.
神父费雷拉
Father Ferreira.
我放弃了
I've given up.
我们已经很久未见了
So long since we have met.
你不说点啥
Would you say something?
啥...
What...
我能对你说啥？此种场合
Can I say to you on such an occasion?
如你对我有丝毫同情，说点啥
If you have any pity for me, say something.
你已，你已... 你已在此住了很久了吗
Have you, have you... have you been living here for long?
大约一年，我以为
About a year, I suppose.
- 这是啥地方？
- What is this place?
- 一座庙，我学习之处
- A temple. Where I study.
我也在狱中
I'm also in a prison.
在长崎某地
Somewhere in Nagasaki.
我不知确切位置
I don't know precisely where.
我知
I know.
你是我的导师
You are my teacher.
- 你曾是我的忏悔师，我的导师
- You were my confessor, my teacher.
- 我几乎一样
- I'm much the same.
做件简单的事
Do a single simple thing.
跟我说，神父
Tell me, Padre.
跟我说你同意
Tell me you agreed.
我是？我是真的显得如此不同？
Do I? Do I really seem so different?
尊敬的泽野大人每天都在书写
The honorable Sawano spends his days writing...
...关于天文学
...about astronomy.
井上大人的命令
Inoue Sama's order.
这里有丰富的知识
There is great knowledge here
但医学和天文学仍有很多要教
but in Medicine and Astronomy much remains to be taught.
我很乐意帮忙
I'm happy to help.
欣慰的是...
It is fulfilling to...
...终于对这个国家有用了
...finally be of use in this country.
你快乐吗？神父
And you're happy, Father?
我那样说了
I said so.
说起你正在写的另一本书
Mention the other book you are writing.
叫作《显伪录》
It is called <i>Kengiroku.
注：<i>Kengiroku http://www.worldcat.org/title/kengiroku-disclosure-of-falsehoods/oclc/122712825)
它展示了基督教的时代
It shows the eras of Christianity
及驳斥那些教义
and refutes the teachings of those.
你理解标题吗？
Do you understand the title?
告诉他
Tell him.
它意味着...
It means...
...欺骗，披露或揭穿...
...deceit, disclosed or unmasked...
...如你喜欢一个更华丽的读法
...if you prefer a more florid reading.
连奉行官，他...
There's also the Inquisitor, he...
...赞美它，他说它写得很好
...praises it, he says it is well done.
- 这是真的。
- It's the truth.
你用真的当毒药
You use the truth like poison.
传教士这样说多滑稽啊
What a funny thing for a priest to say.
这是残酷的，残酷!
This is cruel. Cruel!
此举比用任意酷刑扭曲一个人的灵魂更坏
Worse than any torture to twist a man's soul in this way
我觉得你定是在说你自己...
I think you must speaking of yourself...
...而非泽野忠庵
...not of Sawano Chūan.
谁
Who?
他！他对你只是费雷拉
Him! He is Ferreira only to you.
他如今叫泽野忠庵
He is Sawano Chūan now.
一个找到安宁的男人
A man who has found peace.
让他引导你走他的路
Let him guide you along his path.
慈悲之路
The path of mercy.
那只意味着你放弃自我
That means only your abandoned self.
没人能左右别人的灵魂
No one should interfere with another man's spirit.
帮助他人，这是佛的方式
To help others, is the way of the Buddha.
而你们的方式亦然
And your way too,
两种宗教在这方面是同样的
The two religions are the same in this.
无需争取任何人到一边或另一边...
It is not necessary to win anyone over to one side or another...
...当分享如此之多时
...when there is so much to share.
继续
Go on.
有人告诉我，让你放弃信仰
I've been told to get you to abandon the faith.
- 这个...
- This...
- 这个来自“穴吊”
- This is from the Pit.
你被紧绑，因此你不能动
You're tied, so you can't move.
然后倒吊
And hung upside down.
弄个切口
An incision is made.
你感到血液滴下
You feel the blood dripping down.
一滴连一滴
Drop by drop.
所以它不会流到你头上...
So it doesn't run to your head...
...你不会死得太快
...and you won't die too soon.
踏上你的圣像
Step on your Jesus.
如今你是此地最后一个传教士，神父
You are the last priest left here now, Padre.
- 我确信井上大人定会高兴的把...
- I'm sure Inoue Sama will be pleased to put
...后继者穴吊
...an heir to the Pit.
他是个务实的人，神父
He is a practical man, Padre.
而非残酷者
Not a cruel one.
我苦撑于此国长达15年
I have labored in this country for 15 years.
我了解它多过你
I know it better than you.
我们的宗教扎不了根
Our religion does not take root...
...在这个国家
...in this country.
因为树根已经被磨烂了
Because the roots have been torn up.
不，因为这国家是个沼泽
No. Because this country is a swamp.
这里长不了东西
Nothing grows here.
植物尚为幼苗根即腐烂
Plant is sapling here and the roots rot.
天主教在此有过生长及繁茂的时候
There was a time when Christianity here grew and flourished here.
何时？
When?
何时？在你的时代，神父
When? In your time, Father.
在你的时代，在你变得像...
In your time, before you became like...
象谁？象他们
Like who, like them?
罗德里格斯，请听着
Rodriguez, please listen.
日本人只相信他们所扭曲的...
The Japanese only believe in their distortion...
...我们的真理，因此他们根本不信
...Of our gospel. So they did not believe at all.
他们从未信过
They never believed.
你怎能如此说这些？
How can you say that?
从圣·弗朗西斯·泽维尔时代到你自己的时代
From the time of St. Francis Xavier through your own time.
有过成千上万的皈依者在此
There were hundreds of thousands of converts here.
成百的？
Hundreds?
皈依者，是的
Converts, yes!
弗朗西斯·泽维尔来这里教日本人关于神之子...
Francis Xavier came here to teach the Japanese about the son of God...
...但首先，他必须问如何提到神
...but first he had to ask how to refer to God.
大日，他被告知
DaiNiChi, he was told.
要我告诉你他们的大日吗？
Shall I show you their DaiNiChi?
看吧
Behold.
神之子在那儿
There is the son of God.
神只有一个儿子
God's only begotten son.
在圣经中，耶稣在第三天复活
In the scriptures, Jesus rose on the third day.
在日本，神的儿子...
In Japan the son of God...
...每天升起
...rises daily.
日本人想不出一种超越自然界的存在
The Japanese can not think of an existence beyond the realm of nature.
对他们来说，没有什么能超越人类
For them nothing transcends to human.
不
No!
他们无法构想我们的天主教之神的理念
They can't conceive of our idea of the Christian God!
不，你错了，你错了
No, you're wrong. You're wrong.
他们敬拜神！神！我们的主
They worship God! God! Our Lord!
他们赞美耶稣之名
They praise the name of Deus!
那只是神的另一个名字，他们从不知道
That's just another name for a God, they never knew.
我看到人死了
I saw men die!
我也看到了
I did too.
为耶稣！
For Deus!
与他们的信仰烧在一起
On fire with their faith.
你的烈士可能烧着了，神父
Your martyrs might have been on fire, Father.
但那不是基督徒的信仰
But it was not of the Christian faith.
我目睹他们死去，我目睹他们死去，他们不是为虚无而死
I saw them die. I saw them die. They did not die for nothing.
他们不是
They did not.
他们为你而死，罗德里格斯
They're dying for you, Rodriguez.
你救了多少
How many did you save?
当你踏踩我们主之脸之时
When you trampled on the face of our Lord?
你自己身边有多少人
How many beside yourself?
我不知道
I don't know.
当然不象你可能救的那么多
Certainly not as many as you may help.
你试图为自己的弱点辩护
You're trying to justify your own weakness.
愿神怜悯你！
God have mercy on you!
哪个神？哪一位？
Which God? Which one?
我们说，山...
We say Sangewalede...
我很抱歉，实际上你尚未学过此语言，是吗
I'm sorry, you haven't learned the language though really, have you?
这儿有句俗话
There is a saying here
江山易改
Mountains and rivers can be moved.
本性难易
But man's nature can not be moved.
这很睿智，像极此处
It's very wise, like so much here.
我们在日本找到了我们的本性，罗德里格斯
We find our original nature in Japan, Rodriguez.
也许是通过找寻神而被领悟
Perhaps this was meant by finding God.
你是个耻辱
You're a disgrace.
你是个耻辱，神父
You're a disgrace, Father.
我不能
I can't.
我再也不能那样叫你了
I can't even call you that anymore.
好的
Good.
我如今有了日本名
I have a Japanese name now.
一位妻子及孩子
A wife and children.
我全继承了她们，从一名被处决者那里
I inherited them all from an executed man.
- 你觉得如何？
- How do you feel?
- 他已向你展示仁慈之路
- He has shown you the path of mercy.
- 我希望你接受它
- I hope you take it.
你何不就吊我入穴？
Why don't you just hang me in the pit?
你被奉行所传唤
You are called to the Inquisitor's office.
神父，你为他们来到这儿，而他们都恨你
Padre, you came here for them and they all hate you.
尽情侮辱我，这只会给我更多勇气
Insult me all you like, it just give me more courage.
今晚你会需要它
You will need it tonight.
你是个好男人，神父。你受不了苦难。但你错了，对别人来说
You are a good man, Padre. You can not stand suffering. You're wrong, for others.
井上大人说你今晚会成为一个弃教者
Inoue Sama says you will be a apostatize tonight.
他对费雷拉是对的...
He was right about Ferreira...
...他对你也是对的
...and he's right about you.
赞美他(拉丁语)
LauDate Eum
神帮帮我。耶稣帮帮我
God help me. Jesus help me.
在果园里，您说过
In the garden, you said
“您的灵魂是悲伤的，甚至接近死亡。”
"Thy soul is sorrowful even unto death."
(马太福音，26章38节，此处比原文少了些词。果园，指Gethsemane，客西马尼园，耶稣蒙被犹大出卖之地)
我会为您流血，我会...
I would bleed for you, I would...
我会为您去死
I would die for you.
若我了解您
If I knew you.
您与我同在于此吗
Are you here with me?
神父
Padre.
原谅我
Forgive me.
神父
Padre.
我要做忏悔
I came to make confession!
神父
Padre!
原谅我，神父
Forgive me, Padre!
阻止它！阻止它！阻止它！阻止噪声
Stop it! Stop it! Stop it! Stop the noise!
阻止它！来人帮帮他
Stop it! Someone help him!
你要什么
What do you need?
不是我，那下边
Not me, down there.
有人受痛苦
there is a man in agony!
守卫在酣睡还打着鼾，像只野狗
And the guard is sound asleep and snoring like a wild dog!
你以为那噪声是守卫
You think that noise is the guard?
难以置信
Incredible!
泽野！告诉他，说它是啥
Sawa! Tell him, say what it is.
它不是守卫也不是打鼾
It is not the guard and it's not snoring.
是基督徒
It's Christians.
他们五个，事实上
Five of them in fact.
全被吊在穴里
All hanging in the pit.
你找到墙上的话了吗
Have you found the words on the wall?
赞美他(拉丁语)
LauDaTe E u m
赞美他
Praise him.
我用石头刻下它们，当我此牢房时...
I cut them there with a stone when I was in this cell...
...跟你一样
...like you
闭嘴
Be quiet.
不要，不要跟我说，你没权力跟我说
Don't, don't speak to me, you have no right to speak to me.
噢，我有，因为你就像我
Oh, I do, because you were just like me.
你看到耶稣及客西马尼园，相信你的考验和他的一样
You see Jesus and Gethsemane believe that your trial is the same as his.
穴吊的苦难远远不及耶稣所受
That's far from the Pit of suffering too just like Jesus.
而这些人没有你的骄傲
but they don't have your pride.
他们永远不会把自己同耶稣相比
They would never compare themselves to Jesus.
你有权利吗？让他们受苦？
Do you have the right? To make them suffer?
我在此牢听过这般苦难的痛苦
I heard the cries of suffering in this same cell.
于是我做了
And I acted.
你原谅自己，你原谅自己
You excuse yourself, you excuse yourself,
那是黑暗之灵
that is the spirit of darkness!
你会为他们做啥？祈祷吗？
What would you do for them? Pray?
又得到什么回应？
And get what in return?
只有更多的苦难
Only more suffering.
唯你能结束的苦难，不是神！- 离我远点！
A suffering only you can end, not God! - Go away from me.
我也祷告，罗德里格斯
I pray too, Rodriguez.
那没用
It doesn't help.
继续
Go on.
祷告
Pray.
但要睁眼祷告
But pray with your eyes open.
你可以赦免他们
You can spare them.
他们呼唤救命，就像你呼唤神
They call out for help, just as you call to God.
他沉默，而你不必
He is silent and you do not have to be.
他们该弃教！弃教
They should apostatize! Apostatize!
神救我，弃教
God help me, apostatize!
但他们已弃教
But they have apostatized.
很多次
Many times over.
他们因你在此，罗德里格斯
They're here for you, Rodriguez!
只要你不放弃信仰，他们就不能获救
As long as you don't apostatize, they can not be saved.
传教士应该效仿基督
A priest should act in imitation of Christ.
如果基督在此。
If Christ were here.
基督在此
Christ were here.
他会做的
He would have acted.
为他们着想弃教
Apostatized for their sake.
不，不，他在这儿，基督在这儿，我只是听不到他
No. No, he's here, Christ is here. I just can't hear him.
给神看你爱他
Show God you love him!
救他所爱者之命
Save the lives of the people he loves!
有东西...
There is something...
...比教会的审判更为重要
...more important than the judgement of the Church.
你如今将去完成...
You are now going to fulfill...
...最痛苦且从未被履行过的慈悲之举
...the most painful act of love that has ever been performed.
这只是形式，只是形式
It's only a formality. Just a formality.
<b>现在来吧
Come ahead now.
<b>这没什么
It's alright.
<b>踏踩我
Step on me.
<b>我理解你的痛苦
I understand your pain.
<b>我生于这世上...
I was born into this world...
<b>...就为分担人痛苦
...to share men's pain.
<b>我背负这十字架...
I carried this cross...
<b>...免除你们的痛苦
...for your pain.
<b>你命现与我同在
Your life is with me now.
<b>踏吧
Step.
“弃教的保罗”
"Apostate Paul!"
<i>那是在1641年...
<i>It was in the year 1641...
<i>...在我首次航海旅日期间
<i>...during the first of my voyages to Japan.
<i>我，迪特尔·阿尔博瑞奇...
<i>That I, Dieter Albritch...
<i>...发现了最特别的事...
<i>...came upon the most extraordinary story
<i>...在这些纸页中
<i>...in these pages.
天主教
Christian.
非天主教
Unchristian.
<i>作为一家伟大的荷兰贸易公司的医生...
<i>As a physician in a great Dutch trading company...
<i>...我四处旅行
<i>...I traveled widely.
天主教
Christian.
<i>然而没有任何一桩我所详述于此日记的奇观...
<i>But none of the wonders I have recounted in this journal...
<i>...被如此评论...
<i>...has been so commented on...
<i>...作为稀奇事件...
<i>...as the curious matter...
<i>...弃教传教士的
<i>...of the apostatized priests.
天主教
Christian.
<i>我比任何欧洲记者更接近此国之谜
<i>I came closer than any European chronicler to the enigma of this country.
非天主教
Unchristian.
<i>...及学习失联传教士的生活
<i>...and to learning of the lives of the lost priests.
<i>在某种程度上，奉行官，会突袭住宅...
<i>In a way, the Inquisitor, would raid homes...
<i>...并搜查任何藏有天主教图像之物
<i>...and search for any objects with hidden Christian images.
天主教
Christian.
<i>两位传教士被要求检查这些东西，并核实它们的用途
<i>The two priests were required to examine these things, and verify their use.
<i>我甚至偶尔，亲自观察它们
<i>I even on occasion, observed them myself.
<i>荷兰人是唯一被允许在日本进行贸易的欧洲人
<i>The Dutch were the only Europeans allowed to trade in Japan.
<i>所有船支被搜查，以确保他们不走私宗教物品
<i>All ships were searched to warrant they were not smuggling religious objects.
<i>没有任何带有十字、圣人图像的东西或念珠能通过
<i>Nothing bearing the images of the cross, the saint or rosary could pass.
<i>尽管每次必查，少数物品难免被走私进来
<i>Despite every attempt, a few things inevitably were smuggled in.
<i>天主教
<i>Christian.
<i>然后它就会使日本人痛苦，仿佛血已溢出
<i>And then it was as distressing to the Japanese, as if blood had been spilled.
我们被教导要爱那些跟我们不和者
We were taught to love those who discord us.
我对他们毫无感觉
I feel nothing for them.
只有我们的主能审判你的心
Only our Lord can judge your heart.
你说，我们的主
You said our Lord.
我怀疑
I doubt it.
<i>泽野忠庵死后，另一位传教士承担了其职责
<i>When Sawano Chūan died, the other priests assumed his duties.
<i>并以区别对待他们
<i>And performed them with distinction.
<i>但是这次，我观察到一个相当大的语言技巧
<i>But this time, I observed yet a quite considerable skill with the language.
<i>且似乎对他的处境很满意
<i>And seemed to be at peace with his situation.
我有个好消息
I have good news.
江户有人死了
A man has died in Edo.
冈田三右卫门
Okada Sanyemon.
你将继承其名字
You will take his name.
就像他一样
Just as he did.
他有一个家庭，妻子，儿子
He had a household and wife and son.
你可以把她当作你的妻子
You can take her as your wife.
男人工作得最好当他不再单身时
A man works best when he's not alone.
你应当知道这岛上的生月和五岛
You should know that on the islands of Ikitsuki and Goto.
仍有许多农民自以为是基督徒
There are still many farmers who think themselves as Christian.
你喜欢那样吧？他们可以继续当基督徒
You like that? They can continue to be Christian.
你可能会对此感到满意
You may take some satisfaction in that.
因为根被砍断了
Because the roots are cut.
沼泽里长不了任何东西
Nothing grows in a swamp.
是的，日本就是那种国家
Yes, Japan is that kind of country.
那宗教，那些你带给我们的基督徒
The religion, the Christian you brought us
已成为奇怪的东西，它变了
has became a strange thing. It's changed.
你不是败给我
You were not defeated by me.
你败给了日本这个沼泽
You were defeated by this swamp of Japan.
欢迎
Welcome.
<i>冈田三右卫门住进江户
<i>Okada Sanyemon lived in Edo
<i>度过他的余生
<i>for the remaining years of his life.
<i>大约10年后，我获准访问江户
<i>Some 10 years later, I was allowed to visit Edo.
<i>日本人随意地闲聊了冈田三右卫门
<i>The Japanese gossiped freely about Okada Sanyemon.
<i>奉行官井上再三要求他的弃教誓言
<i>The Inquisitor Inoue demanded repeated vows of apostasy from him.
<i>他们则说，那沦落的传教士全都迅速积极的回应了他们
<i>And they say, the fallen priest applied them all quickly and vigorously.
我听说奉行官派他的人找你
I heard the Inquisitor sent his men for you.
有麻烦吗？- 不
Was there trouble? - No.
他们只是想确保我写下那证据
They only wanted to make sure I wrote that corroboration.
我的谴责信
My letters of denunciation.
谢谢你
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
你没有任何事需要谢我
You have nothing to thank me for.
为在此陪我
For being here with me.
神父
Padre.
不，不，我不是
No, no. I'm not.
我不再是了
I'm not anymore！
我是个沦落的传教士
I'm a fallen priest
但你是最后一个传教士
But you are the last priest left.
你仍能听我的忏悔
You could still hear my confession.
不！我不能
No! I can't!
我仍为我的所为痛苦，神父
I still suffer for what I did, Padre.
我背叛了你
I betrayed you.
我背叛了我的家人
I betrayed my family.
我背叛了我们的主
I betrayed our Lord.
求您
Please!
听我忏悔吧
Hear my confession.
神父
Padre.
主啊，我反抗您的沉默
Lord, I fought against your silence.
<b>我陪同你受苦
I suffered beside you.
<b>我从不沉默
I was never silent.
我知
I know.
但是即使...
But even...
...神沉默我的一生
...if God had been silent my whole life.
在此每天
To this very day.
事事我为，事事我已为
Everything I do, everything I've done.
对他说话
Speaks of him.
那是我在沉默中听到了您的声音
It was in the silence that I heard your voice.
<i>奉行官继续坚持定期查验...
<i>The Inquisitor continued to insist on periodic examinations...
<i>...所有疑似基督徒
<i>...Of all suspected Christians.
<i>冈田三右卫门，未能从中豁免
<i>Okada Sanyemon, was not exempt from this.
<i>在某种程度上，这就决定了他的榜样永远不会被遗忘
<i>In a way, it was determined to never let his example be forgotten.
<i>也许尤其是...
<i>Perhaps most particularly...
<i>...通过传教士本人
<i>...by the priest himself.
<i>在1667年，一个宗教图像在护身符中被发现
<i>In the year 1667. A religious image was discovered inside an amulet.
<i>属于一名唤作吉次郎的仆人
<i>Belonging to a servant called Kichijiro.
<i>仆人说他是在赌博中赢得，从未看过里面
<i>The servant said he had won at gambling. Had never looked inside.
<i>且从未从冈田三右卫门处得到此护身符
<i>And could never have gotten the amulet from Okada Sanyemon.
<i>因为他总是在看守下
<i>Since he was always under guard.
<i>此仆人，吉次郎，被带走
<i>The servant, Kichijiro, was taken away.
<i>此后，冈田三右卫门本人，被密切监视
<i>After that, Okada Sanyemon himself, was carefully watched.
<i>在我最后的旅行期间，在1682，我问及他
<i>During my last voyage, in 1682, I asked about him.
<i>日本人则热切回答
<i>And the Japanese were eager to reply.
<i>最后的传教士从未承认天主教的神...
<i>The last priest never acknowledged the Christian God...
<i>...没有通过文字或图像
<i>...not by word or symbol.
<i>他从未说过他
<i>He never spoke of him.
<i>且从未祷告过
<i>And never prayed.
<i>甚至在他死去时
<i>Not even when he died.
<i>他所信仰的事，早已结束
<i>The business of his faith, was long ended.
<i>三名守卫看守棺材
<i>Three guards stood watch over the coffin.
<i>直至其可被带走，只是为了被确定
<i>Until it could be taken away, just to be certain.
<i>只有他的妻子被短暂允许看到遗体
<i>Only his wife was briefly allowed to view the body.
<i>并把一件简陋的纪念须刀放入
<i>And placed there a humble memory gatana.
<i>以辟开邪恶之灵
<i>To ward off evil spirits.
<i>没有迹象表明她哭了
<i>There was no indication that she wept.
<i>遗体以佛教的仪礼处置
<i>The body was treated in the Buddhist manner.
<i>他还被赐予一个死去的法号
<i>And he was given a posthumous Buddhist name.
<i>那个曾名罗德里格斯的男人
<i>The man who was once Rodriguez.
<i>按他们之意结束
<i>Ended as they wanted.
<i>而当我第一次看见他
<i>And as I first saw him.
<i>与神失联
<i>Lost to God.
<i>但是否如此
<i>But as to that.
<i>实际上
<i>In deed.
只有神能回答
<i>Only God can answer.
为日本的基督徒及他们的牧师 为上帝的最大荣耀
For the Japanese Christians and their pastors.For the greater glory of God.
导演：马丁·斯科塞斯
Martin Scorsese
Author：Shusaku Endo
原著：遠藤周作 えんどう しゅうさく [1923—1996] 出版于1966
中文字幕：dottob 20170207-0217
<b><i>Psagmeno.com</b> <font color=#ff0000>Subtitles / Screenshots / Trailers</font>